<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>graphql on Dgraph Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/tags/graphql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in graphql on Dgraph Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2020, Dgraph Labs, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 07:41:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://blog.dgraph.io/tags/graphql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing GraphQL schemas</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/designing-graphql-schemas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 07:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/designing-graphql-schemas/</guid>
      <description>This post made it to top 10 on HackerNews front page. Do engage in discussion there and show us love by giving us a GitHub star.
GraphQL has taken the app development world by storm because of its immense benefits. GraphQL adoption by UI development teams has brought in a new wave of flexibility in API design, productivity across frontend-backend teams, intuitiveness in expressing UI data requirements, and accessibility to powerful tooling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GraphQL Summit story</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/graphql-summit-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 14:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/graphql-summit-19/</guid>
      <description>We took part in the recently held GraphQL Summit in San Francisco.
The conference was exciting, and it had a great line up of talks. As expected, the enthusiasm in the GraphQL community was unmatchable.
We took part as one of the platinum sponsors of the event, and we also unveiled the new GraphQL API for Dgraph. Read along as we share our experience at the event as it unfolded.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Native GraphQL Database: Challenges, Learnings and Future</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/building-native-graphql-database-dgraph/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 02:13:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/building-native-graphql-database-dgraph/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;GraphQL is not a Graph DB query language &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s a replacement for REST APIs.&amp;rdquo;
 That&amp;rsquo;s my standard opening statement whenever talking about Dgraph&amp;rsquo;s choice of the query language.
Most people who don&amp;rsquo;t know GraphQL assume it&amp;rsquo;s a graph database query language. Most people who know GraphQL wonder how a graph database is being powered by it.
Our focus at Dgraph has always been on helping you build apps using an amazingly advanced graph database.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dgraph&#39;s recap of GraphQL Conf - Berlin 2019</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/graphql-conf-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 14:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/graphql-conf-19/</guid>
      <description>We took part in the recently held GraphQL conference in Berlin. The experience was fascinating, and we were amazed by the high voltage enthusiasm in the GraphQL community. Now, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t help ourselves from sharing this with Dgraph&amp;rsquo;s community! This is the story of the GraphQL conference in Berlin.
The GraphQL connection If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering what does Dgraph has to do with GraphQL, here&amp;rsquo;s the answer. Dgraph had set its eyes and placed its bet on GraphQL very early.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>