<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DevRel on Dgraph Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/tags/devrel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DevRel on Dgraph Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2017, Dgraph Labs, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 14:30:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://blog.dgraph.io/tags/devrel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dgraph tutorials series - 2: UID operations, updating nodes, and traversals</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/tutorial-2-getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 14:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/tutorial-2-getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the second episode of getting started with Dgraph. In the last episode of the tutorial, we learned some of the basics of Dgraph. Including how to run the database, add new nodes and predicates, and query them back.
In this episode, we&amp;rsquo;ll build the above Graph and learn more about operations using the UID (Universal Identifier) of the nodes. Specifically, we&amp;rsquo;ll learn about:
 Querying and updating nodes, deleting predicates using their UIDs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dgraph tutorials series - 1: Getting started</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/tutorial-1-getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 14:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/tutorial-1-getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to getting started with Dgraph. Dgraph is an open-source, transactional, distributed, native Graph Database. Here is the first episode of the tutorial series on using Dgraph.
In this tutorial, we&amp;rsquo;ll learn how to build the following graph on Dgraph,
In the process, we&amp;rsquo;ll learn about:
 Running Dgraph using the dgraph/standalone docker image. Running the following basic operations using Dgraph&amp;rsquo;s UI Ratel,  Creating a node. Creating an edge between two nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Releasing Dgraph v1.1.0</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/release-v1.1.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/release-v1.1.0/</guid>
      <description>Dgraph is an open-source, transactional, distributed, native graph database. Ever since the internet explosion, the data not just has been growing in size, but also in its complexity and connectedness. Dgraph is built as an effort to enable and simplify the development of scalable cloud applications that could continue to thrive even when the data is highly connected and involved.
Set on this path, embracing open source all along the way, the first production-ready, major release v1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dgraph&#39;s recap of GraphQL Conf - Berlin 2019</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/graphql-conf-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 14:30:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/graphql-conf-19/</guid>
      <description>We took part in the recently held GraphQL conference in Berlin. The experience was fascinating, and we were amazed by the high voltage enthusiasm in the GraphQL community. Now, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t help ourselves from sharing this with Dgraph&amp;rsquo;s community! This is the story of the GraphQL conference in Berlin.
The GraphQL connection If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering what does Dgraph has to do with GraphQL, here&amp;rsquo;s the answer. Dgraph had set its eyes and placed its bet on GraphQL very early.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating 10,000 GitHub Stars</title>
      <link>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/10k-github-stars/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 01:23:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.dgraph.io/post/10k-github-stars/</guid>
      <description>Dgraph is celebrating the milestone of reaching 10,000 GitHub stars 🎉.
This wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have happened without all of you, so we want to thank the awesome community for being with us all the way along. This milestone comes at an exciting time for Dgraph.
Let&amp;rsquo;s do quick time-travel through our journey, gaze at our milestones, and wrap it up with a glance through the exciting things in the pipeline.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>